The youthful perspective on the future,
وجهة نظر الشباب حول المستقبل،
the present perspective on the future
النظرة الحالية عن المستقبل
and the future, mature perspective on the future --
والنظرة الثاقبة المستقبلية حول المستقبل --
I'd like to try and bring all those three tenses together
سأحاولُ دمج كل الحالات الثلاث معًا
in one identity tonight.
في هوية واحدة الليلة.
And you could say that the poet, in many ways,
ويمكنكم القول بأن الشاعر، في طرقٍ عدة،
looks at what I call "the conversational nature of reality."
ينظرُ فيما أسميه "الطبيعة التخاطبية للواقع".
And you ask yourself:
ويمكنكم سؤال أنفسكم:
What is the conversational nature of reality?
ما هي الطبيعة التخاطبية للواقع؟
The conversational nature of reality is the fact
الطبيعة التخاطبية للواقع هي في الحقيقة
that whatever you desire of the world --
كل ما ترغبون به من العالم --
whatever you desire of your partner in a marriage or a love relationship,
ما ترغبون به من شركائكم في الزواج، أو من علاقة حب،
whatever you desire of your children,
ما ترغبون به من أولادكم،
whatever you desire of the people who work for you or with you,
ما ترغبون به من الأشخاص الذين يعملون لك أو تعملون معهم،
or your world --
أو عالمكم الذي تعيشون فيه --
will not happen exactly as you would like it to happen.
لن يحدث تماما كما ترغبون أن يحدث.
But equally,
ولكن على حدٍ سواء،
whatever the world desires of us --
ما يرغبه العالم منا --
whatever our partner, our child, our colleague,
مهما كان شريكنا، وأطفالنا، وزملاؤنا،
our industry,
وقطاعاتنا،
our future demands of us,
ومتطلبات المستقبل منا،
will also not happen.
لن تحدث أيضًا.
And what actually happens
ما يحدثُ حقاً
is this frontier between what you think is you
هو تلك الحدود بين ما تعتقدون أنه أنتم
and what you think is not you.
وما تعتقدون أنه ليس أنتم.
And this frontier of actual meeting
وهذه الحدود للالتقاء الحقيقي
between what we call a self and what we call the world
بين ما نطلق عليه الذات، وما نسميه العالم
is the only place, actually, where things are real.
هو المكان الوحيد، في الواقع، حيث الأمور حقيقية.
But it's quite astonishing,
ولكنه لمدهش إلى حدٍ كبير،
how little time we spend at this conversational frontier,
كيف نمضي وقتًا قليلًا في هذه الحدود التخاطبية،
and not abstracted away from it in one strategy or another.
ولا نواصل سيرنا بعيدًا عنه في وضع خطة بارعة أو أي شيء آخر.
I was coming through immigration,
قدمتُ إلى هنا من خلال الهجرة،
which is quite a dramatic border at the moment,
التي هي حدود مثيرة للدهشة تماما في وقتها
into the US last year,
داخل أمريكا العام الماضي،
and, you know, you get off an international flight
وكما تعلمون، حضرتُ على متن طائرة دولية
across the Atlantic,
عبر المحيط الأطلسي،
and you're not in the best place;
ولستُ في أفضل مكان،
you're not at your most spiritually mature.
ولستُ على الأكثر في نضوجٍ روحاني.
You're quite impatient with the rest of humanity, in fact.
كنتُ نافذ الصبر مع بقية البشر، في الواقع.
So when you get up to immigration with your shirt collar out
لذلك، عندما قابلتُ موظف الهجرة مرتديًا قميصًا ذات ياقة خارجية
and a day's growth of beard,
ونمو لحية يوم،
and you have very little patience,
ومتحليًا بالصبر القليل جدًا،
and the immigration officer looked at my passport
ونظر موظف الهجرة في جواز سفري
and said, "What do you do, Mr. Whyte?"
وقال، "ماذا تعملُ سيد وايت؟"
I said, "I work with the conversational nature of reality."
قلتُ، "أعمل مع الطبيعة التخاطبية للواقع."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he leaned forward over his podium
وانحنى إلى أمام منصته
and he said, "I needed you last night."
وقال، "كنتُ بحاجة إليك الليلة الماضية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I said, "I'm sorry,
وقلتُ له، "أنا آسف،
my powers as a poet and philosopher only go so far.
تذهبُ نفوذي كشاعر وفيلسوف بعيدًا جدًا،
I'm not sure I can --"
ولستُ متأكدًا أنني أستطيع --"
But before we knew it,
ولكن قبل أن نعرفُ ذلك،
we were into a conversation about his marriage.
دخلنا في محادثة حول زواجه.
Here he was in his uniform,
كان مرتديًا زي العمل،
and the interesting thing was,
وكان الشيء المثير للاهتمام،
he was looking up and down the row of officers
كان ينظرُ إلى أعلى وإلى أسفل صف الموظفين
to make sure his supervisor didn't see
ليتأكد بأن مشرفه لا يرى
that we was having a real conversation.
أننا نتبادلُ محادثة حقيقية.
But all of us live at this conversational frontier
لكن يعيشُ جميعنا الحدود التخاطبية
with the future.
مع المستقبل.
I'd like to put you in the shoes of my Irish niece,
أرغبُ في وضعكم مكان ابنة أخي/أختي الإيرلندية
Marlene McCormack,
مارلين ماكورماك،
standing on a cliff edge on the western coast of Spain,
تقفُ على حافة منحدر صخري للساحل الغربي من أسبانيا،
overlooking the broad Atlantic.
وتطلُ إلى المحيط الأطلسي الواسع.
Twenty-three years old, she's just walked 500 miles
تبلغُ من العمر 23 عاما، وسارت لتوها 500 ميلًا
from Saint Jean Pied de Port on the French side of the Pyrenees,
من ميناء سانت جين بييد من الجانب الفرنسي لجبال البرانس،
all the way across Northern Spain,
على طول الطريق عبر شمال إسبانيا،
on this very famous, old and contemporary pilgrimage
في هذا الطريق المقدس قديمًا وحديثًا، والمشهور جدًا،
called the Camino de Santiago de Compostela --
الذي يدعى كامينو سانتياغو كومبوستيلا.
the Path to Santiago of Compostela.
الممر إلى سانتياغو لكومبوستيلا.
And when you get to Santiago, actually,
وعندما تصل سانتياغو، في الواقع،
it can be something of an anticlimax,
يمكنُ أن يكون هناك شيء من خيبة الأمل،
because there are 100,000 people living there
لأنه يعيش هناك 100,000 شخص
who are not necessarily applauding you as you're coming into town.
وليس ضروريًا أن يهتفوا لكم حال وصولكم المدينة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And 10,000 of them are trying to sell you a memento of your journey.
ويحاولُ 10,000 منهم بيعكم تذكارًا لرحلتكم الدينية.
But you do have the possibility of going on for three more days
ولكن يكون لديكم إحتمالية المكوث لثلاثة أيام أخرى
to this place where Marlene stood, called, in Spanish, Finisterre,
لهذا المكان حيث وقفت مارلين، ويسمى بالإسبانية فينستري،
in English, Finisterre,
وبالإنجليزية فينستير،
from the Latin, meaning "the ends of the earth,"
تعني باللغة اللاتينية، "نهاية الأرض،"
the place where ground turns to ocean;
المكان حيثُ تتحول الأرض إلى محيط،
the place where your present turns into the future.
المكان حيث يتحول حاضركم إلى مستقبلكم.
And Marlene had walked this way --
وسارت مارلين هذه الطريق --
she just graduated as a 23-year-old from the University of Sligo
لقد تخرجت للتو وعمرها 23 عامًا من جامعة سليغو
with a degree in Irish drama.
بشهادة في الدراما الإيرلندي.
And she said to me, "I don't think the major corporations of the world
وقالت لي: "لا أعتقدُ بأن الشركات الكبرى في العالم
will be knocking on my door."
ستطرقُ بابي."
I said, "Listen, I've worked in corporations all over the world
قلتُ لها: "اسمعي، عملتُ في شركات في جميع أنحاء العالم
for decades;
لعقود،
a degree in drama is what would most prepare you for the adult --
ستؤهلك الشهادة في الدراما لكبار --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
corporate world."
شركات العالم."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But she said, "I'm not interested in that, anyway.
ولكنها قالت: "لستُ مهتمة بذلك، على أية حال.
I don't want to teach drama, I want to become a dramatist.
لا أرغبُ في تدريس الدراما، أريدُ ان أكون كاتبة مسرح.
I want to write plays.
أريدُ أن أكتب مسرحيات.
So I walked the Camino in order to give myself some courage,
لذلك سرتُ طريق الكامينو لأعطي نفسي بعض الشجاعة،
in order to walk into my future."
لكي أسير نحو مستقبلي."
And I said, "What was the most powerful moment you had on the whole Camino,
وقلتُ لها: "ما هي أقوى لحظة شعرتِ بها في طريق كامينو بالكامل،
the very most powerful moment?"
اللحظة الأقوى جدًا؟"
She said, "I had many powerful moments,
قالت: "شعرتُ بعدة لحظات قوية،
but you know, the most powerful moment was post-Camino,
لكن وكما تعلم، كانت أقوى اللحظات ما بعد كامينو،
was the three days you go on from Santiago and come to this cliff edge.
كانت الأيام الثلاثة التي ذهبتُ فيها من سانتياغو ووقفتُ على حافة هذا المنحدر.
And you go through three rituals.
ودخلتُ عبر ثلاثة طقوس.
The first ritual is to eat a tapas plate of scallops" --
الطقوس الأولى، تناول طبق مقبلات من سرطانات البحر"
or if you're vegetarian,
وإذا كنتم نباتيون،
to contemplate the scallop shell.
عليكم التفكير في قشرة سرطان البحر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Because the scallop shell has been the icon and badge of your walk,
لأن لدى قشرة سرطان البحر الرمز، والعلامة المميزة لسيركم،
and every arrow that you have seen along that way
وكل سهم ترونه على طول الطريق بهذا الشكل
has been pointing underneath a scallop shell.
تم الإشارة له تحت قشرة سرطان البحر.
So really, this first ritual is saying:
حقًا، تقولُ الطقوس الأولى هذا:
How did you get to this place?
كيف وصلتم إلى هذا المكان؟
How did you follow the path to get here?
وكيف اتبعتم الممر لتصلوا إلى هنا؟
How do you hold the conversation of life when you feel unbesieged,
وكيف تجرون المحادثة عن الحياة عندما تشعرون بأنكم غير محاصرون،
when you're unbullied,
وعندما لا يُخيفكم أحد،
when you're left to yourself?
وعندما تتصرفون على سجيتكم؟
How do you hold the conversation of life that brings you to this place?
كيف تجرون المحادثة عن الحياة التي تحضركم إلى هذا المكان؟
And the second ritual is that you burn something that you've brought.
والطقوس الثانية هي عليكم حرق شيء أحضرتموه معكم.
I said, "What did you burn, Marlene?"
قلت، "ما الذي قمتِ بحرقه مارلين؟"
She said, "I burned a letter and two postcards."
قالت، "أحرقتُ رسالةً وبطاقتي بريد."
I said, "Astonishing.
قلت: "مذهل!
Twenty-three years old and you have paper.
ثلاثة وعشرون عامًا ولديك ورقة!
I can't believe it."
لا أصدق ذلك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm sure there's a Camino app
أنا متأكد أنّ هناك تطبيق كامينو
where you can just delete a traumatic text, you know?
حيثُ يمكنكم حذف نص مفجع، أتعلمون بذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It will engage the flashlight,
ستستخدمُ المصابيح اليدوية،
imbue it with color
وتصبغُ بالألوان
and disappear in a firework of flames.
وتختفي في لهب الألعاب النارية.
But you either bring a letter or you write one there,
ولكن عليكم إحضار إمّا رسالة أو كتابتها هناك.
and you burn it.
وتحرقونها.
And of course we know intuitively what is on those letters and postcards.
وبطبيعة الحال نعرفُ بديهيًا ما تحوية الرسالة والبطاقات البريدية.
It's a form of affection and love that is now no longer extant, yeah?
إنه شكل من أشكال المودة والحب الذي لم يعد له وجود اليوم، أليس كذلك؟
And then the third ritual:
وبعد ذلك الطقوس الثالثة:
between all these fires are large piles of clothes.
ما بين كل الحرائق وأكوام الملابس الضخمة.
And you leave an item of clothing
وتتركون قطعة ملابس
that has helped you to get to this place.
ساعدتكم للوصول إلى هذا المكان.
And I said to Marlene, "What did you leave at the cliff edge?"
وقلتُ لمارلين، ماذا تركتِ على حافة المنحدر؟"
She said, "I left my boots --
قالت، "تركتُ حذائي
the very things that I walked in, actually.
الشيء الذي سرتُ فيه، في الواقع.
They were beautiful boots, I loved those boots,
كان حذاءً جميلًا، لقد أحببتُ هذا الحذاء،
but they were finished after seven weeks of walking.
ولكنه أنهى مهمته بعد سبعة أسابيع من السير.
So I walked away in my trainers,
لذلك فسرتُ بحذائي الرياضي،
but I left my boots there."
ولكني تركتُ حذائي هناك."
She said, "It was really incredible.
وقالت: "كان ذلك مدهشًا حقًا!
The most powerful moment was, the sun was going down,
كانت اللحظات الأقوى، عندما انحدرت الشمس إلى أسفل،
but the full moon was coming up behind me.
ولكن كان يعلو القمر الكامل من خلفي،
And the full moon was illuminated by the dying sun in such a powerful way
وكان يضاءُ القمر الكامل عن طريق غياب الشمس في هذه الطريقة القوية
that even after the sun had dropped below the horizon,
حتى وبعد أن هبطت الشمس إلى ما وراء الأفق،
the moon could still see that sun.
ما زال يرى القمر تلك الشمس.
And I had a moon shadow,
وكان لدي ظلٌ قمري
and I was looking at my moon shadow walking across the Atlantic,
وكنتُ أنظرُ في ظلّي القمري وهو يسيرُ عبر الأطلسي،
across this ocean.
عبر هذا المحيط.
And I thought,
واعتقدتُ،
'Oh! That's my new self going into the future.'
’إلهي! هذه ذاتي الجديدة تسيرُ إلى المستقبل.
But suddenly I realized the sun was falling further.
ولكن أدركتُ فجأةً بأن الشمس كانت تنحدرُ أكثر.
The moon was losing its reflection,
وكان القمر يفقدُ انعكاساته،
and my shadow was disappearing.
وكان ظلّي يختفي.
The most powerful moment I had on the whole Camino
اللحظة الأقوى التي شعرتُ فيها وأنا أسيرُ كامينو بأكمله
was when I realized I myself had to walk across that unknown sea
كانت عندما أدركتُ أنه ينبغي عليّ بنفسي السير عبر ذلك البحر المجهول
into my future."
إلى مستقبلي."
Well, I was so taken by this story,
حسنًا، انبهرتُ بهذه القصة،
I wrote this piece for her.
وكتبتُ هذا المقطع من أجلها.
We were driving at the time;
كنا نقودُ الحافلة في ذلك الوقت،
we got home, I sat on the couch,
ووصلنا المنزل، وجلستُ على الأريكة،
I wrote until two in the morning --
وكتبت حتى الساعة الثانية صباحا
everyone had gone to bed --
ذهب الجميع إلى النوم
and I gave it to Marlene at breakfast time.
وأعطيتها إلى مارلين وقت تناول وجبة الفطور.
It's called, "Finisterre," for Marlene McCormack.
سميتها، "فينستر" من أجل مارلين ماكورماك.
"The road in the end
"الطريق في النهاية
the road in the end taking the path the sun had taken
الطريق في النهاية يكتظُ الممر وتهبطُ الشمس
into the western sea
إلى داخل البحر الغربي
the road in the end taking the path the sun had taken
الطريق في النهاية يكتظُ الممر وتهبط الشمس
into the western sea
إلى داخل البحر الغربي
and the moon
والقمر
the moon rising behind you
يعلو القمرُ خلفك
as you stood where ground turned to ocean:
عندما تقفين حيثُ تتحولُ الأرض إلى المحيط
no way to your future now
لا سبيلَ إلى مستقبلك الآن
except the way your shadow could take,
عدا السبيل الذي تمكّن ظلك سيره،
walking before you across water, going where shadows go,
السيرُ قبل عبورك الماء، والذهاب حيثُ تذهب الظلال،
no way to make sense of a world that wouldn't let you pass
لا سبيل لجعل العالم ذو معنى الذي منعك من العبور
except to call an end to the way you had come,
عدا اختيار نهاية للطريق الذي حضرت منه،
to take out each letter you had brought
وإتلاف كل رسالة أحضرتيها
and light their illumined corners;
وإضاءة زواياها المضيئة،
and to read them as they drifted on the late western light;
وقراءتها وهي تنحرفُ على الضوء الغربي الأخير،
to empty your bags
لتفريغ حقائبك
to empty your bags;
لتفريغ حقائبك،
to sort this and to leave that
لترتيب هذا وترك ذاك
to promise what you needed to promise all along
لضمان ما احتجتِ إليه للتعهد المستمر
to promise all along,
لللتعهد المستمر
and to abandon the shoes that brought you here
والتخلي عن الحذاء الذي أحضرك إلى هنا
right at the water's edge,
قرب حافة النهر،
not because you had given up
ليس لأنك استسلمت
but because now,
لكن لأنه الآن،
you would find a different way to tread,
ستجدين طريقًا مختلفة لتسيري فيه،
and because, through it all,
ولأن، خلال كل هذا،
part of you would still walk on,
سيبقى جزءً منك يسير دومًا،
no matter how,
لا يهمُ كيف،
over the waves."
فوق الأمواج."
"Finisterre."
" فينيستر"،
For Marlene McCormack --
إلى مارلين ماكورماك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
who has already had her third play performed
التي تم عرض ثلاث مسرحيات لها فعلًا
in off-off-off-off-Broadway --
بعيدًا جدًا عن برودوي
in Dublin.
في دبلن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But she's on her way.
ولكنها في طريقها.
This is the last piece.
هذا هو المقطع الأخير.
This is about the supposed arrival at the sum of all of our endeavors.
إنه حول الوصول المفترض في مجمل محاولاتنا.
In Santiago itself --
في سانتياغو نفسها
it could be Santiago,
يمكنُ أن تكون سانتياغو،
it could be Mecca,
يمكن أن تكون مكة المكرمة،
it could be Varanasi,
يمكنُ أن تكون فاراناسي،
it could be Kyoto,
يمكنُ أن تكون كيوتو،
it could be that threshold you've set for yourself,
يمكنُ أن تكون تلك البداية التي وضعتموها لأنفسكم
the disturbing approach to the consummation of all your goals.
النهج المثير للقلق لتحقيق كل أهدافكم.
And one of the difficulties about walking into your life,
وإحدى الصعوبات حول المضي قدمًا إلى حياتكم،
about coming into this body,
حول وجودكم بهذه الهئية،
into this world fully,
إلى هذا العالم بأكمله،
is you start to realize
هي بداية إدراككم
that you have manufactured three abiding illusions
بأنكم صنعتم ثلاثة أوهام مستمرة
that the rest of humanity has shared with you since the beginning of time.
التي شاطرتكم بقية البشرية فيها منذ بداية التاريخ.
And the first illusion is that you can somehow construct a life
الوهم الأول هو، أنكم تستطيعون بطريقة أو بأخرى بناء حياة
in which you are not vulnerable.
بحيثُ لا تكونون عرضة للخطر.
You can somehow be immune to all of the difficulties
يمكنكم نوعًا ما أن تكونوا في مأمن من كل الصعوبات
and ill health and losses
وسوء الصحة والخسائر
that humanity has been subject to since the beginning of time.
التي يصابُ بها كل البشر منذ بداية التاريخ.
If we look out at the natural world,
لو نظرنا إلى العالم الطبيعي،
there's no part of that world
لا يوجد أي جزء من هذا العالم
that doesn't go through cycles of, first, incipience,
لا يمرُ عبر هذه الدورات، أولاً، البداية،
or hiddenness,
أو التخفي،
but then growth, fullness,
ولكن بعد ذلك التطور، والكمال،
but then a beautiful, to begin with, disappearance,
ولكن بعد ذلك الجمال، لتبدأ مع الزوال،
and then a very austere, full disappearance.
وثم القسوة الشديدة، الزوال بالكامل.
We look at that, we say, "That's beautiful,
ننظرُ في ذلك، ونقول، "هذا جميل،
but can I just have the first half of the equation, please?
لكن هل يمكنني الحصول على أول نصف المعادلة، لو سمحت؟
And when the disappearance is happening,
وعندما يحدثُ الزوال،
I'll close my eyes and wait for the new cycle to come around."
أغلقُ عيناي وأنتظر دورة جديدة لتأتي هنا وهناك."
Which means most human beings are at war with reality
التي تعني بأن معظم البشر في صراع مع الواقع
50 percent of the time.
%50 من الوقت.
The mature identity
الهوية الناضجة
is able to live in the full cycle.
هي القدرة على العيش في دورة كاملة.
The second illusion is,
الوهم الثاني هو،
I can construct a life in which I will not have my heart broken.
أستطيع بناء حياة بحيثُ لن يتحطم قلبي.
Romance is the first place we start to do it.
فالحب أول مكان للقيام بذلك.
When you're at the beginning of a new romance or a new marriage,
فعندما يكون أحدكم في بداية حب جديد أو زواج جديد،
you say, "I have found the person who will not break my heart."
يقول: "وجدتُ الشخص الذي لن يحطم قلبي."
I'm sorry;
أنا آسف:
you have chosen them out unconsciously for that exact core competency.
لقد تمّ اختيارك دون وعي لهذه الأهلية الأساسية بالضبط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They will break your heart.
سيتحطم قلبك.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because you care about them.
لأنك تهتم بهم.
You look at parenting, yeah?
تنظرُ في تربية الأبناء، نعم؟
Parenting: "I will be the perfect mother and father."
تربية الأبناء: "سأكون أمًا أو أبًا مثالية."
Your children will break your heart.
سيحطمُ أولادك قلبك.
And they don't even have to do anything spectacular or dramatic.
ولا يحتاجون حتى القيام بأي شيء مذهل أو محزن.
But usually, they do do something spectacular or dramatic --
لكن في العادة، يقومون بعمل شيء مذهل أو محزن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to break your heart.
لتحطيم قلبك.
And then they live with you as spies and saboteurs for years,
ومن ثم يعيشون معك كجواسيس ومخبرين لسنوات،
watching your every psychological move,
يراقبون كل حركاتك النفسية الذهنية
and spotting your every weakness.
ويكتشفون كل ضعفك،
And one day,
وفي يومٍ ما،
when they're about 14 years old,
عندما يبلغون 14 عاما،
with your back turned to them,
وظهرك لهم،
in the kitchen,
في المطبخ،
while you're making something for them --
بينما تعدُ لهم شيئًا من الطعام،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the psychological stiletto goes in.
يطعنك الخنجر النفسي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And you say, "How did you know exactly where to place it?"
وتقول: "كيف عرفت أين تطعنه بالضبط؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And they say,
ويقولون:
"I've been watching you for --
"كنتُ أراقبك منذ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
a good few years."
سنوات قليلة."
And then we hope that our armored, professional personalities
ومن ثم نأملُ بأن شخصياتنا المدرّعة، والمهنية
will prevent us from having our heart broken in work.
ستقينا من تحطم القلوب في العمل.
But if you're sincere about your work,
لكن إذا كنت مخلصًا في عملك،
it should break your heart.
ينبغي أن يتحطم قلبك.
You should get to thresholds
عليك الحصول على البدايات
where you do not know how to proceed.
حيثُ لا تعرفُ كيفية المضي قدمًا.
You do not know how to get from here to there.
لا تعرفُ كيفية التحرك من هنا إلى هناك.
What does that do?
ماذا يفعلُ هذا؟
It puts you into a proper relationship with reality.
إنه يضعك في العلاقة السليمة مع الواقع.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because you have to ask for help.
لأنه يتوجتُ عليك طلب المساعدة.
Heartbreak.
تحطم القلوب.
We don't have a choice about heartbreak,
لا نملكُ خيارًا حول تحطم القلوب،
we only have a choice of having our hearts broken
نملكُ فقط الخيار لتحطم قلوبنا
over people and things and projects that we deeply care about.
من خلال الأشخاص والأشياء والمشاريع التي نهتم بها بعمق.
And the last illusion is,
والوهم الأخير هو،
I can somehow plan enough and arrange things
أستطيع نوعًا ما التخطيط بما فيه الكفاية وتنظيم الأمور
that I will be able to see the path to the end
التي ستمكنني من رؤية الطريق للنهاية
right from where I'm standing,
من حيثُ أقف بالضبط،
right to the horizon.
إلى الأفق تماما.
But when you think about it,
لكن عندما تفكرُ حولها،
the only environment in which that would be true
فالبيئة الوحيدة حيث سيكون ذلك حقيقية
would be a flat desert,
ستكون صحراء خاوية،
empty of any other life.
خالية من أية حياة أخرى.
But even in a flat desert,
لكن حتى في الصحراء الخاوية،
the curvature of the earth would take the path away from you.
ستبعدك انحناءات الأرص بعيدًا عن طريقك.
So, no;
لذلك، لا!
you see the path,
ترى الطريق،
and then you don't
ومن ثم لا تراه
and then you see it again.
وثم تراه مجددًا.
So this is "Santiago,"
لذلك هذه هي "ساتياغو"،
the supposed arrival,
الوصول المفترض،
which is a kind of return to the beginning all at the same time.
هي نوع من عودة جميعنا إلى البداية في نفس الوقت.
We have this experience of the journey,
لدينا هذه التجربة من الرحلة،
which is in all of our great spiritual traditions,
التي هي في داخل تقاليدنا الروحية الرائعة،
of pilgrimage.
للرحلة الدينية.
But just by actually standing in the ground of your life fully,
ولكن مجرد الوقوف الفعلي على أرضية حياتك بأكملها،
not trying to abstract yourself into a strategic future
محاولًا عدم تجريد ذاتك داخل المستقبل المخطط له
that's actually just an escape from present heartbreak;
الذي هو في الحقيقة مجرد هروب من الحزن الراهن،
the ability to stand in the ground of your life
القدرة على الوقوف على أرضية حياتك
and to look at the horizon that is pulling you --
والنظر في الأفق الذي يسحبك
in that moment,
في هذه اللحظة،
you are the whole journey.
أنت الرحلة بأكملها.
You are the whole conversation.
أنت التخاطب الكلي.
"Santiago."
"سانتياغو".
"The road seen, then not seen
"رؤية الممر، ثم عدم رؤيته
the road seen, then not seen
رؤية الممر، ثم عدم رؤيته
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take
تختبىء التلال، ثم يظهرُ لك الممر الذي عليك سيره
the road seen, then not seen
رؤية الممر، ثم عدم رؤيته
the hillside hiding then revealing the way you should take,
تختبىء التلال، ثم يظهرُ لك الممر الذي عليك سيره
the road dropping away from you
ينحدرُ الطريق بعيدًا عنك
as if leaving you to walk on thin air,
كأنه يتركك تسيرُ على الهواء الرقيق،
then catching you,
وثم يجذبك،
catching you,
يحذبك،
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
يرفعك عالياً، حينما اعتقدت بأنك ستسقط،
catching you,
يجذبك،
holding you up, when you thought you would fall,
يرفعك عاليًا، حينما اعتقدت بأنك ستسقط،
and the way forward
والممر إلى الأمام،
the way forward always in the end
والممر إلى الأمام دومًا في النهاية
the way that you came,
الممر الذي سلكته،
the way that you followed, the way that carried you into your future,
الممر الذي سلكته الممر الذي حملك إلى مستقبلك،
that brought you to this place,
الممر الذي أحضرك إلى هذا المكان.
no matter that it sometimes had to take your promise from you,
بغض النظر إن كان أحيانًا يسلبك وعودك،
no matter that it always had to break your heart along the way:
بعض النظر أنه دومًا يحطم قلبك على طول الطريق
the sense
الاحساس
the sense of having walked from deep inside yourself
احساسك بالسير من داخل نفسك العميقة
out into the revelation,
إلى المُجاهرة،
to have risked yourself
لتعريض نفسك للخطر
for something that seemed to stand both inside you and far beyond you,
لشيءٍ بدا أنه يقفُ داخلك وبعيدًا عنك كثيرًا،
and that called you back in the end
وعاد بمناداتك في النهاية
to the only road you could follow,
إلى الممر الوحيد الذي تمكنت من تتبعه
walking as you did, in your rags of love
والسيرُ كما فعلت، في بساط الحب
and speaking in the voice that by night became a prayer for safe arrival,
والتحدثُ بصوتٍ أصبح كالصلاة ليلًا للوصول الآمن،
so that one day
وذات يوم
one day you realized
وذات يوم أدركت
that what you wanted had actually already happened
بأن كل ما أردته حدث فعلًا
one day you realized
ذات يوم أدركت
and long ago
قبل وقتٍ طويل
and in the dwelling place in which you lived before you began,
وفي مكان السكن حيثُ عشت قبل أن تبدأ
and that
وأنّ
and that every step along the way,
وأنّ كل خطوة على طول الطريق،
every step along the way,
كل خطوة على طول الطريق،
you had carried the heart and the mind and the promise
حملتَ القلب والعقل والعهد
that first set you off and then drew you on,
لأول انطلاقة لك، وثم اعتمدت عليها،
and that
وأنّ
and that you were more marvelous
وأنك كنت أكثر روعة
in your simple wish to find a way
في رغبتك الواضحة للعثور على الطريق
you were more marvelous
كنت أكثر روعة
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach
من الأسطح المذهّبة لأي نهاية تمكنت من الوصول إليها
you were more marvelous in that simple wish to find a way
كنت أكثر روعة في رغبتك الواضحة للعثور على الطريق
than the gilded roofs of any destination you could reach:
من الأسطح المذهّّبة لأي مكانٍ تمكنت من الوصول إليه
as if, all along,
كانك، على طول،
you had thought the end point might be a city with golden domes,
اعتقدت أنه قد تكون نقطة النهاية مدينةً ذات قباب ذهبية،
and cheering crowds,
ومهاتفة الحشود،
and turning the corner
وتحويل الزواية
at what you thought was the end of the road,
لما اعتقدت أنه كان نهاية الطريق،
you found just a simple reflection,
وجدت مجرد انعكاس بسيط
and a clear revelation beneath the face looking back
والمُجاهرة الواضحة تحت الوجه المنعكس
and beneath it another invitation,
وتحته دعوة أخرى،
all in one glimpse
كل شيء في لمحة واحدة
like a person
مثل شخص
like a person or a place you had sought forever
مثل شخص أو مكان سعيت إليه دومًا
like a bold field of freedom that beckoned you beyond;
مثل بابٍ واضحٍ للحرية يفتحُ أمامك،
like another life
كحياة أخرى،
and the road
والطريق
the road still stretching on."
وما زال الطريق يتمدد."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم! شكرًا لكم.
You're very kind. Thank you.
أنتم لطيفون، شكرًا لكم.